<tool id="PartsGenie" name="PartsGenie" version="1.0.0">
    <description>An integrated tool for optimizing and sharing synthetic biology parts</description>
    <requirements>
        <requirement type="package" version="1.0.0">partsgenie_client</requirement>
    </requirements>
    <command detect_errors="exit_code"><![CDATA[
        python -m partsgenie_client
        '$url'
        '$enzymes_file'
        '$taxonomy_id'
        '$parts'
    ]]></command>
    <inputs>
        <param name="enzymes_file" type="data" format="xml" label="Enzymes File" />
        <param name="taxonomy_id" type="integer" value="83333" label="Chassis taxonomy ID" />
        <section name="adv" title="Advanced Options" expanded="false">
            <param name="url" type="text" value="partsgenie.micalis.inrae.fr" label="PartsGenie server URL" />
        </section>
    </inputs>
    <outputs>
        <data name="parts" format="xml" label="${tool.name} - ${enzymes_file.name}" />
    </outputs>
    <help><![CDATA[
Introduction

PartsGenie allows for the design and optimisation of novel, reusable synthetic biology parts.
This user interface consists of a number of components:

Parts: an interactive drag-and-drop interface for assembling parts from features such as promoters, ribosome binding sites (RBS) and coding sequences (CDS).
Feature: a panel allowing for the specification of parameters relating to individual features.
Filters: a panel for specifying filters to consider in optimising the parts.
Results: a panel for displaying and querying results of the part optimisations.
In addition, there is also the functionality for saving optimised parts to an instance of JBEI-ICE.

Parts

The Parts panel offers a simple drag-and-drop interface for defining multiple parts from a collection of features represented as buttons.

The user can build up a part by dragging-and-dropping features from the palette of grey buttons. Tablet and smartphone users can add features to the part by double-clicking on the feature button in the palette.

The features available are described below in the feature section.

Individual parts may be named.

Upon selecting a given feature, the Feature panel becomes visible, allowing the specification of parameters specific to that feature. Examples of this include an amino acid sequence for a CDS, or a translation initiation rate (TIR) for an RBS. The feature will be bordered by a red warning box until these necessary features are specified.

Note that a restriction exists such that a RBS must be immediately followed by a CDS. Again, the RBS will be bordered by a red warning box if this restriction is not adhered to.

In the case of optimising RBS or CDS, an Organism must be specified from the autofill field.

Multiple parts may be specified, by either clicking the '+' icon, or by duplicating a specified part through the Copy icon. Individual parts can be viewed and edited by clicking the numbered pagination panel. Designs may be deleted, as can individual features within parts.

Upon completing the set of parts, and adhering to all restrictions, the Submit button will turn green, and the job may be submitted.

Feature

The Feature panel is viewed on selecting a given feature in the Design panel.
The Feature panel is specific to the selected feature, which can be one of the following types:

Defined sequence.
Randomised sequence.
Sequence of defined melting temperature.
Origin of replication.
Promoter.
Ribosome binding site.
Coding sequence.
Fixed coding sequence.
Terminator.

In each case, an individual Feature can be named.

In the cases of Defined sequence, Origin of replication, Promoter and Terminator, the only required parameter is the nucleotide Sequence itself. This sequence is fixed and not optimised by the PartsGenie algorithm.

Randomised sequence requires a Length of the sequence, which is periodically mutated through the optimisation sequence to optimise the part as a whole.

A Sequence of defined melting temperature requires a defined melting temperature (Tm).

Ribosome binding sites require a desired translation initiation rate TIR.

Coding sequences require an Amino acid sequence to be specified, which may be extracted automatically through the Search Uniprot facility:

Filters

The Filters facility allow for the specification of constraints that must be applied during the optimisation process. A Max repeating nucleotides may be specified, preventing long runs of repeating nucleotides which impede synthesis of designed parts. Excluded codons and Excluded restriction sites may be specified.
In all cases, such Filters should be kept to a minimum, as specifying too many unnecessary constraints will increase optimisation time and, in some cases, prevent optimisation altogether. For example, specifying either too few max repeating nucleotides, or too many excluded codons or restriction sites may result in the design space being constraint to such an extent that no valid reverse translation of an amino acid coding sequence exists.

Results

Upon completion of an optimisation job (including one or more parts), the Results panel is displayed.
The Results panel allows for the inspection of all optimised parts, allowing for the part as a whole, and individual features, to be viewed.

Individual features can be viewed by selecting the feature, and metadata specific to that feature can be inspected. (This may include TIR for a RBS, or Codon Adaptation Index (CAI) - a measure of how optimised codon usage is for the target host organism - for CDS features.)

Results

ICE

Upon clicking the ICE button, the user is presented with a form for logging into an instance of JBEI ICE. The required parameters are URL of the JBEI ICE instance, Username and Password. Finally, a Group may be specified, allowing any submitted designed part to be shared between members of a JBEI ICE defined group.
Once a user has logged into ICE, the ICE button will turn green, after which, parts may be Saved to JBEI ICE from the Results panel.

Further details

Further details are available from the publication describing this work. Please cite this reference in any scientific disclosure that utilises PartsGenie.
PartsGenie: an integrated tool for optimising and sharing synthetic biology parts. 
Neil Swainston, Mark Dunstan, Adrian J Jervis, Christopher J Robinson, Pablo Carbonell, Alan R Williams, Jean-Loup Faulon, Nigel S Scrutton, Douglas B Kell. 
bioRxiv, 189357 
https://doi.org/10.1101/189357
    ]]></help>
</tool>